The subject we are going to learn is called formal languages and automata theory. It is
also called theory of computation. It is a core course for B. Tech or B. E. in computer
science and engineering in many of the universities. In some universities it is also a course
for B. Tech I. T. In some places in mathematics department also it is a course for M. S.
Mathematics. The topics that will be covered in this course are as follows. First we shall
start with grammars. The four types of grammars some examples ambiguity and so on. Next we
consider the finite state automaton which is the simplest machine model. Then we go
on to context free grammars study in detail some of the properties of context free grammars.
Next we study about the push down automaton which is the machine model for context free
grammars. Then we go on to the most general type of the machine Turing machines and we
study about the decidability properties and also complexity in Turing machines.
We shall cover some of the advanced topics like grammar systems, regulator rewriting,
L systems and so on. And finally, we will end up with two new models of computation the
DNA computing and the membrane computing. The books which could be followed for this
course are as follows. The first book is written by me and Rama. Introduction to
formal languages automata theory and computation published by Pearson education in 2009.
Harpcraft, Mortwani and Wulman introduction to automata theory languages and computation
that is also Pearson education. Peter Lin's and introduction to formal languages and automata.
M. Sipser introduction to theory of computation. John Martin introduction to the languages
and theory of computation. These are some of the books there could be many more books which
you could follow but as a text book you could follow the first one and the second one.
This subject formal languages and automata theory or you can also call it as theory
of computation. It started in the year 1959 with the formal definition given by
Nam Shomsky. He tried to define what is a grammar, what is a mathematical model of a grammar.
The motivation was to study parsing in natural languages like English. So, he tried to look at
the parse trees of the natural language sentences and then try to define what is a grammar. So,
let us take some sentences in English and see how they can be parsed. Take a simple sentence first.
The man ate the fruit. How can this sentence be parsed? Starting with the sentence this can
be considered as a noun phrase and a verb phrase. I will call it as noun phrase one and verb
phrase. Then the verb phrase itself splits into verb and noun phrase two. Noun phrase
one splits into article and noun one. Article is the noun is man. N one is man noun one.
Verb is eight. Noun phrase two itself can be split as article and noun two. Article is the noun two
is fruit. So, this is the parse tree for this sentence. The man ate the fruit. The parse tree
or syntax tree for the grammar. We also call it as a derivation tree. If you go from sentence to
the sentence symbol to the sentence, it is a derivation. If you go from the sentence to the
sentence symbol trying to construct the tree in the bottom of manner, it is parsing. So,
let us look at the rules here. The rules will be of this form. The sentence symbol goes to noun
phrase one and verb phrase. The sentence symbol goes to noun phrase one and verb phrase. Similarly,
for each one of that, we will write the rules. Then noun phrase one goes to article and noun
one. Article goes to the noun one goes to man and verb phrase goes to verb and noun phrase two.
Verb goes to eight. Noun phrase two goes to article and noun two. Again, article goes to these already
there. Noun two goes to. So, using these rules, these are called rules or productions. Rules or
productions are sometimes called production rules. And using these rules, you can derive this
sentence. The man ate the fruit from S. I am not distinguishing between this T and this T.
As an article, we are taking it as the. Now, how is the derivation done? Starting with start
symbol. Yes, you use the first rule. Now, in the derivation, I am applying a rule that is written
by a double arrow. A rule, there is a left hand side and there is a right hand side. And the left
hand side is rewritten as the right hand side. So, this arrow is read as rewritten as. S is
rewritten as noun phrase one and verb phrase. This double arrow represents directly derives.
Directly derives. So, S directly derives noun phrase one and verb phrase and noun phrase
one directly derives article and noun one. This directly derives this. So, when you get
something from something else, this is called a sentential form. Something like that is
called a sentential form. This verb phrase remains as it is. So, this is a sentential
form. In this sentential form, noun phrase one is rewritten as article and noun one. So,
this sentential form directly derives this sentential form. That is written as a double arrow.
Next, you have to use a single rule. Article can be written as the rule is article can
be written as the noun one and verb phrase. They are remaining as they are. Then here noun
one is rewritten as man. You are applying the rule noun one goes to man. So, noun one
is rewritten as man verb phrase remains as it is.
Please note that I am using only one rule at any step. In the next step, the man the verb phrase is
written as verb and noun phrase two. So, it is rewritten as verb and noun phrase two using
this rule. Then the man this is a sentential form. In this sentential form, I am applying
one rule for verb. What is the rule for verb? Verb goes to eight. So, verb goes to eight. Noun
phrase two remains as it is. The man eight noun phrase two is rewritten as article and noun two
using this rule. Then the next step article is rewritten as D and the last step noun two is
rewritten as fruit using this rule. This is called a derivation. This is called a derivation. This
double arrow is really a relationship between sentential forms. So, if you have a sentential
form alpha, you derive beta from that. What does that mean? You get beta from alpha by the application
of a single rule. So, it represents a relation between sentential forms. Sentential forms
are actually strings over non-terminals and terminals. I will mention what is a non-terminal
in a moment. Here you note that there is a distinction between these words and these syntactic
categories. These are syntactic categories. Noun verb phrase etcetera. So, these noun or
verb phrase is rewritten as something else. So, they are called non-terminals. Whereas,
once you get to the leaves of this tree, the man ate the fruit. They cannot be rewritten
as something else. The derivation terminates there. So, these are called terminals. Terminals,
non-terminals and terminals. Usually, we denote by capital N the set of non-terminals. By
set of terminals. So, if you consider the total alphabet V, this is called the total alphabet.
V is N union T and the start symbol S. S is the start symbol. S is the start symbol or
sentence symbol. It is one of the non-terminals. S belongs to N and what are sentential forms?
What is a sentential form? It is a string belonging to V star. We know what is meant by V star,
is not it? We have already considered set operations on sigma star. Sigma is an alphabet. Here,
we are taking the alphabet as V. So, if you look at this double arrow as a relationship
between alpha and beta, what does the double arrow star denote? Then this is a relation. What
does double arrow star denote? If you say alpha, dash goes to beta dash. What does that
mean? Beta dash is obtained from alpha dash in 0 or more steps. Here, beta is obtained
from alpha in one step by the application of a single rule. You keep on applying rules.
Finally, from S, you are deriving the sentence, the man ate the fruit. So, usually what is
this called star? It is called the reflexive transitive closure. Usually, this is the
reflexive transitive closure of. So, double arrow star beta, alpha dash, double arrow star
beta dash means, beta dash is obtained from alpha dash in 0 or more steps. So, a grammar
mainly consists of a set of non-terminals, a set of terminals, a set of production
rules usually denote by P and a start symbol. So, a grammar consists of a grammar G is equal
to N T P S. It is a four tuple N T P S of four tuple G is equal to N T P S, where N is a
finite set of non-terminals, T is a finite set of terminals, T is a finite set of productions
or production rules or rules. S belonging to N is the start symbol. Here, you must realize
that N intersection T is a disjoint element, non-terminals and terminals are disjoint.
The definition of a grammar with Chomsky a. Now, there is something vague about P. P is
something like the left hand side is rewritten as a right hand side. In this example, it so
happens that the left hand side is a single non-terminal. It is a single syntactic category
in this example. Right hand side is a string. In general, what can be the form of the
production rule? A much general form is possible. We will come to that in a moment. Before that,
I would try to take another example of a sentence to make it more convincing. Take this sentence,
the peacock is a beautiful bird. Here again, the sentence can be rewritten as noun phrase
1 and verb phrase. Noun phrase 1 is rewritten as article 1, noun 1. Article 1 is the noun
1 is peacock. Verb phrase is written as verb, article 2, adjective, noun 2. So, verb is article
2 is a. Adjective is beautiful. Noun 2 is the parse tree or the derivation tree or the
syntax tree for this sentence. Now, how do the rules look like? The first one is like
this. The second one is noun phrase 1 is article 1. There are two articles, D and A here. Noun
phrase 1 goes to article 1 and noun 1. Article 1 goes to D. Noun 1 goes to peacock and verb
phrase goes to verb, article 2, adjective, noun 2. And verb phrase 1 goes to verb,
verb goes to is, article 2 goes to A. Adjective goes to beautiful and noun 2 grows to. These
are the production rules. In a similar manner, you can derive something like this. I will
write the derivation for this also, but before that I want you to look at one of the things.
In this example, in this derivation, sentence has been rewritten as noun phrase 1 and verb
phrase 2. At the next step, I have replaced noun phrase 1 as article and noun 1. There
is no necessity that this should have been done. You could have replaced the verb phrase
also. That could also have been done. The order does not matter. Finally, you have
to end up with this sentence. But in this derivation, I have specifically taken in such
a manner that I always replace the leftmost non-terminal. The leftmost, this is a sentential
form. There are two non-terminals here and I have replaced the leftmost non-terminal
here. Here again, I have replaced the leftmost non-terminal. Then the next step, left
most non-terminal, then the leftmost non-terminal and so on. In each one of the steps, I have
replaced the leftmost non-terminal. It is not necessary. You could have replaced any one
of the non-terminal. That does not matter. If you always replace the leftmost non-terminal,
such a derivation is called the leftmost derivation. This is a leftmost derivation.
In contrast to that, I will take the second example and give another derivation, which is
not leftmost. Now, noun phrase 1 and verb phrase, I am keeping the noun phrase 1 as
it is and replacing the verb phrase by verb article 2, adjective noun 2. Now, I can replace
article 2, noun phrase 1 verb. What is article 2? It goes to A, then adjective, but each step
I am using only one rule. Then, noun phrase 1 verb A, adjective goes to beautiful, using
can replace noun phrase 1. Noun phrase 1 goes to article 1 and noun 1 verb A, beautiful noun
2. Now, article 1 can be replaced by the noun 1 verb this. Then, the next step you can
replace verb as is. The next step you can replace the noun 1 as the peacock is noun 2.
And the last step, the peacock is a beautiful noun 2 is written as bird. Sometimes I replace
the leftmost, sometimes rightmost, sometimes anything. The order does not matter. Some
way, each step you have replaced one non-terminal by the corresponding right hand side. Now,
you could also keep the rightmost non-terminal, always replace the rightmost non-terminal.
Such a thing is also possible, that is called the rightmost derivation. This is neither
a leftmost derivation nor a rightmost derivation. And if you always replace the rightmost
non-terminal, such a derivation is called the rightmost derivation. This is neither
a leftmost nor a rightmost derivation. These two types of derivation rightmost and leftmost
are very important because later on when you learn about compilers, you will realize that
for top down parsing you use leftmost derivation and for bottom up parsing use rightmost derivation.
We consider one more example, which will generate the sentence, Venice is a beautiful
city. The rules for this are given as follows. With the rules given, we shall generate the
sentence like this. First using the first rule we get this. Then using the second rule,
noun phrase one is rewritten as proper noun. Verb phrase remains as it is. Proper noun
is rewritten as Venice. Verb phrase is rewritten as verb and noun phrase two. Then verb is rewritten
as is. Then noun phrase two is rewritten as article, adjective and noun two. Article
is rewritten as a. Adjective is rewritten as beautiful. Noun two is rewritten as city.
So, the grammar generate the sentence Venice is a beautiful city. Now, we have been vague
about the type of production rules. Shamski defined four types of grammar. He defined
type zero, type one, type two and type three grammars. Type zero is the most general
one. Sometimes that is called unrestricted grammar, unrestricted or phrase structure grammar.
Phrase structure, this is the most general type of a grammar. There the rules are of
the form u goes to v, where u belongs to v star n plus v star n plus v star n plus
v star. It is a string of non terminals and terminals, but it should have at least one
non terminal. u should have at least one non terminal and it is a string of non terminals
and terminals. That is why it is written as u belongs to v star n v star. If it is
fully terminal, you cannot rewrite it as something else. The derivation terminates
there. So, you should have at least one non terminal. v can be any string, v belongs to v
star. Please note that v is n union t, v is the total alphabet. Now, type one is also
of this form, but the restriction is the length of the left hand side should be less than
or equal to the length of the right hand side. Length of the right hand side should be greater
than or length of the right hand side should be greater than or equal to the length of the
left hand side. This is also called length increasing grammar. This is also equivalent
to what is known as a context sensitive grammar, context sensitive grammar, but the definition
of a context sensitive grammar is like this. The rules are of the form alpha, a, beta goes
to alpha, gamma, beta where a is a non terminal, alpha and beta are any strings, a is a non
terminal and gamma belongs to v plus. That is a is rewritten as gamma in the context
of alpha and beta. That is why such a rule is called a context sensitive, but these definitions
are equivalent, they are equivalent definitions. You can easily see that, but a formal proof
also I will try to give after a few lectures, sometimes later. This type of a grammar generally
we take this one, this is called type 1 grammar. Now, with this restriction you see that you
cannot have the empty string epsilon on the right hand side, is not it? Epsilon cannot
occur on the right hand side in a type 1 grammar, but sometimes for some purpose you may
want to allow epsilon. If you want to allow epsilon, you just have the rule s goes to
epsilon, add if you want to include the empty string in the language, add this rule s goes
to epsilon where s is the start symbol and in this case you must make sure that s does
not occur on the right hand side of any rule. s is the start symbol, s is the start symbol.
That is if you want to have epsilon also, you must do it only in this way. s is the start
symbol and you can add the rule s goes to epsilon, but you should make sure that s does
not occur on the right hand side of any production. Now, type 2 rules are of the form,
A goes to alpha where A is a non-terminal and alpha belongs to V star. Left hand side you
have a non-terminal and the right hand side you can have any string. Such a rule is called
a context free rule, context free. You can see that the two examples which we consider
the rules are such that on the left hand side you have a non-terminal and on the right hand
side you have a string. They are all context free rules. Both the examples we consider
are context free rules. Mostly European languages they will come under natural languages. It
is easy to give a context free grammar for them, whereas Indian languages it is slightly
difficult to give a context free rules. So, you see that we have taken a general one then
we have given some restrictions on this. We are putting restrictions on the form of production
rules. More and more restrictions we are putting on the putting restrictions on the
form of production rules. So, we put this restriction on type 0 that the length of the right hand
side is greater than the length of the left hand side we get type 1. Then we make a restriction
that the left hand side can be only a non-terminal. Then we get a type 2 or context free rules.
Most of this arithmetic expressions etcetera you can get by context free rules. For example,
this e goes to e expression e plus e, e goes to e star e, e goes to left parenthesis, e right
parenthesis, e goes to identifier. This will generate all arithmetic expressions involving
plus and star. You want to use other operators minus division you can use. This is a context
free grammar generating all arithmetic expressions involving plus and star and wherever you want
to put parenthesis you can put parenthesis using this. Then identifier can be anything
you can just choose your identifier a, b, c, d whatever it is. So, this is an example
of a context free grammar which generates all arithmetic expressions.
The last one type 3 we put more restrictions. The rules are of the form a goes to b or a
goes to where a and b are non-terminals and a, b, a is a terminal, b can be a terminal
or epsilon can be epsilon also. In fact, a slightly more general definition also can
be given. I will do that. This is called actually a regular grammar. There is something called
right linear, left linear, slight extension of it, but they are all equivalent in power.
So, we will deal with that in the next class also. Now, having defined what is a sentential
form, what is a derivation, what is double a raster and so on. What is the language defined
by a gram? If g is a grammar, what is the language generated by? It is denoted by l g
and it is defined as the set of terminal strings w belongs to t star and you can derive
w from s. Starting from s, the set of terminal strings which you can derive, define the language
generated by the grammar. So, the two examples which we took. In the first example, the
language consists of only one string, the man ate the fruit. In the second example,
the language consists of only one string, the peacock is a beautiful boy. In general,
it will not be like that. The language will consist of several strings. For example, here
in this one, this is the start symbol. E is the only start symbol and the only non-terminal
plus star, left parenthesis, right parenthesis, identifier, they are all terminal symbols.
So, from this, you can derive something like i, you can derive many things from here. How
will you derive this here? E goes to E star E, E goes to identifier, E goes to left parenthesis
E, right parenthesis E plus E. This is the derivation thing. You can write a derivation
using this in that manner. Now, as I told you, the Indian languages, they may not permit
context free rules alone. I mean, you cannot describe them using context free rules alone.
You may require context sensitive rules. We will take one example from Hindi and one
example from Tamil. Now, look at this sentence. I will not draw the whole tree, but only
a portion of it. The previous step is, and this co is a case ending. This is a case ending
and the rule applied here is, so this kava changes into kava in the presence of the case
ending, in the context of the case ending. So, such a rule is called a context sensitive
rule. A similar thing can occur in other Indian languages also, if you are familiar
with the Tamil. So, the previous step here will be, and the rule applied is, so this in is
a case ending. It changes to in in the presence of the noun. Only in the presence of the
noun, it changes. The case ending changes, the form of the case ending changes. So,
this changes into this in the context of the noun. So, such a rule is called a context
sensitive type one. This is called type one. The use of this grammars, we will learn more
about grammars, more examples in the next class, but before the use of this is mainly
from compilers, because though they were different from the natural language point
of view, it had lot of application compilers. I told you earlier, the compilers are
called as, it has an analysis part and the synthesis part. The analysis part, you have
the lexical analyzer and parser, which in 1960, when Olgaal 60 was defined. It is a block
structured language. People found that it could be described by what is known as a
baker's normal form BNF. And BNF was nothing but type two grammar, context free grammar. But,
it has been known that you can give the rules in context free, but you may not be able to
capture all the features. Pascal has a very very beautiful grammar, simple grammar which
is type two. In fact, subclass of type two, it has a l l 1 grammar. It can be the compiler
for the Pascal is a top down one, recursive descent parser you have. Whereas, languages
like Fortran and P L 1, which were considered during the 60s, all features of those languages
cannot be captured using context free rules 7. There were some context sensitive aspects,
but when you have considered a context sensitive grammar, the parsed free or syntax free cannot
be drawn easily. It is not very easy to have a parsed free with a type one grammar. Only
type two grammar, something goes into something, you can have a tree like structure. So,
how do you capture the context sensitive features of such languages like Fortran or
P L 1 or later also many languages. The features are not merely context free, some other higher
features are involved. We will learn about them in the due course. So, for that what
they did is the rules they maintained as context free, because that is helpful in parsing.
But then some additional features like attributes or some other control mechanisms were involved,
so that the other properties of the language are also taken care of. So, as we go along the
course we will learn about them. So, there are other ways of putting restriction on the
manner of applying the rules. Here, the four grammars of Chomsky obtained by taking
the most general form unrestricted grammar, then put some restriction then we got type one, put
more restriction we got type two, put more restriction we got type three. So, we were
putting restrictions on the form of the production tools. So, our concentration will be mainly
on type two grammars and type three. These grammars are called generative devices,
they generate the language. In contrast to that you have recognition devices also. So,
a language can also be accepted by an automator. So, formal language theory is more about grammars,
automata theory is more about automata. They go together formal language and automata
formal language theory, automata theory they go together and it is called formal language
and automata theory. So, whenever a language is defined you can define it by means of a generative
device which is known as a grammar. At the same time you can also have an automaton recognizing
that recognizing that language. The simplest automaton is known as the finite state automaton
which corresponds to a type three grammar, finite state automaton. And for type two you
have a pull down automaton which is has a stack and that stack is the major idea in
parsing. And type one you have what is known as a linear bounded automata and for type
one 0 you have the corresponding recognition defined as Turing machines. And one of the
things I should mention is the Turing machine was defined in 1936 itself and even 15 years
before the first computer was built. And at the time the person who defined AM Turing
he was able to foresee what is possible with the computer and what is not possible
with the computer even before the 15 years before the first computer was built. And that
has stood the test of time even what he defined as computability still stands up as the definition
of Turing machine is taken as the model of computation till today. So, we will consider
more examples in the next class.